Abigail Polin, PhD

Carnegie Observatories 813 Santa Barbara Street Pasadena, CA 91101

abigail@caltech.edu abigailpolin.com

I am a joint postdoctoral research fellow sharing a Burke fellowship in theoretical physics at Caltech and a Carnegie fellowship at Carnegie Observatories. I employ a combination of analytic, numerical and high-performance computing techniques to study the physics driving astrophysical explosions and I specialize in connecting that theory to observed transient phenomena.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. in Physics

May 2020

University of California, Berkeley

Advisors: Peter Nugent & Daniel Kasen

Thesis: Pushing the Helium Envelope: Signatures of Normal and Unusual Supernovae from Sub-Chandrasekhar Mass White Dwarf Explosions

M.S. in Physics

May 2015

University of California, Berkeley

B.S. in Physics

December 2012

New York University

RESEARCH APPOINTMENTS

Joint Postdoctoral Research Fellow

2020-Present

Carnegie Fellowship, Carnegie Observatories Burke Fellowship in Theoretical Physics, Caltech

NSF Graduate Research Fellow

2015-2020

University of California, Berkeley

Fellowships & Awards

| | NERSC Early Career Award: High Impact Scientific Achievement Burke Fellowship in Theoretical Physics, Caltech Carnegie Fellowship, Carnegie Observatories | 2021 2020-Present 2020-Present |
|----|---|--------------------------------------|
| | NSF Graduate Research Fellowship | 2015-2020 |
| AL | Wonderfest Science Envoy | 2019-2020 |
| GR | Berkeley Connect Fellowship | 2014-2016 |
| | Outstanding Graduate Student Instructor Award, UC Berkeley | 2014 |

Publication Summary

(see end of CV for complete publication history)

18 journal articles: 7 identifying supernovae belonging to a newly discovered class of transients, which matched our modeled theoretical predictions

Abigail E. Polin

Computing Grants (PI-ED)

| National Energy Research Scientific Computing Center (NERS) ERCAP 2022: | , |
|---|--|
| Perlmutter GPUs Cori KNL CPUs | , |
| NERSC Early Career Award 2021: Early Access to the Perlmutt | er GPU Supercomputer |
| NSF Extreme Science and Engineering Discovery Environment | (XSEDE): |
| XRAC 2021: Stampede2 CPUs | , , |
| DOE INCITE Leadership Computing Award 2023 (co-PI): | |
| Oak Ridge National Laboratory, Summit GPUs Oak Ridge National Laboratory, Frontier CPUs Argonne National Laboratory, Polaris GPUs | $\dots 300,000$ node-hours |
| Awarded Telescope Time (PI-ed) | |
| Las Campanas Observatory: | |
| Magellan: Baade 6.5m telescope — IMACS Optical & FIRE NIR Spectrographs | nights (2022B) nights (2022A) |
| Invited Talks & Conference Proceedings: | |
| SuperVirtual 2022 - From Common to Exotic Transients University of Delaware, Physics and Astronomy Colloquium Chandra Workshop: Supernova Remnants and Their Progenitors NBIA Workshop Radiation Transfer in Astrophysics, Niels Bohr Institute Lawrence Berkeley National Lab, NERSC Awards Seminar Series UC Davis, Physics & Astronomy Seminar Purdue University, Astronomy Seminar Florida State University, Astronomy Seminar Stony Brook University, Astronomy Seminar Harvard University, Galaxy and Cosmology Seminar Northwestern University, Observational Astronomy Seminar UC Santa Barbara, Astronomy Lunch Talk UC Santa Cruz, Astronomy FLASH Talk Caltech, Astronomy Tea Talk Carnegie Observatories, Lunch Talk Haverford College, Physics and Astronomy Colloquium UC Santa Cruz, Pre-Filippenkopalooza Supernovae Meeting KITP, UC Santa Barbara, ZTF Theory Network Summer Meeting Weizmann Institute of Science, Particle Physics and Astrophysics Worksl New York University, CCPP Astrophysics Seminar University of Wisconsin, Milwaukee, Astronomy Seminar | Nov 2021 Apr 2021 Feb 2021 Nov 2020 Oct 2020 Dec 2019 Nov 2019 Oct 2019 Oct 2019 Oct 2019 Oct 2019 Sept 2019 Aug 2018 Aug 2018 |

Abigail E. Polin

| | KITP White Dwarfs Conference, Santa Barbara, CA | Nov 2022 |
|-------|--|----------------------|
| | NASA TDAMM Workshop, Anapolis, MD | $\mathrm{Aug}\ 2022$ |
| BUTEL | AAS Dissertation Talk, Winter Meeting, Honolulu, HI | Jan 2020 |
| | Midwest Workshop on Supernovae and Transients, Ohio State | Sept 2019 |
| RIBU | The Beginnings and Ends of Double White Dwarfs, DARK, Copenhagen | July 2019 |
| ONT | UC Berkeley, Theoretical Astrophysics Seminar | Jan 2018 |
| 00 | Supernovae: The LSST Revolution Workshop, Northwestern | May 2017 |
| | APS March Meeting, Baltimore, MD | Mar 2013 |
| ı | APS March Meeting, Houston TX | Mar 2011 |

MENTORSHIP: ADVISING STUDENT RESEARCH

GRADUATE STUDENTS

Peter Scherbak (Caltech)

Margot Fitz Axen (UT Austin, DOE CSGF Fellow)

Undergraduate Students

Desiree Harvell (CASSI Summer Student: California State University, San Bernardino)

Siddharth Boyeneni (Caltech SURF: Caltech)

Hayden Campos (CASSI Summer Student: Dartmouth)

Wynn Jacobson-Galán (UCSC, now graduate student at UC Berkeley)

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

| ADJUNCT INSTRUCTOR (UC Berkeley) Astro 9: Introduction to Scientific Computing Sole Instructor: in charge of syllabus design and instruction HEAD GRADUATE STUDENT INSTRUCTOR (UC Berkeley) Physics 7A: Introductory Mechanics GRADUATE STUDENT INSTRUCTOR (UC Berkeley) Astro C10: Introduction to General Astronomy Fall 2019 Astro 7A: Introduction to Astrophysics Fall 2017 Astro 250: Introduction to High Performance Computing Physics 7A: Introductory Mechanics ADJUNCT INSTRUCTOR (New York University) Observational Astronomy UC BERKELEY TEACHING CONFERENCE Developer and instructor of a mandatory workshop for first time graduate student instructors COURSEWORK IN TEACHING DEVELOPMENT (UC Berkeley) Physics 198: Progressive Physics Education Spring 2014 Physics 375: Professional Preparation in Teaching Physics Fall 2013 | Outstanding Graduate Student Instructor Award (UC Berkeley) | 2014 |
|--|--|-------------|
| Head Graduate Student Instructor (UC Berkeley) Physics 7A: Introductory Mechanics Graduate Student Instructor (UC Berkeley) Astro C10: Introduction to General Astronomy Astro 7A: Introduction to Astrophysics Fall 2019 Astro 250: Introduction to High Performance Computing Physics 7A: Introductory Mechanics Adjunct Instructor (New York University) Observational Astronomy UC Berkeley Teaching Conference Developer and instructor of a mandatory workshop for first time graduate student instructors Coursework in Teaching Development (UC Berkeley) Physics 198: Progressive Physics Education Physics 198: Physics Pedagogy Seminar Spring 2014 | Adjunct Instructor (UC Berkeley) | |
| Physics 7A: Introductory Mechanics GRADUATE STUDENT INSTRUCTOR (UC Berkeley) Astro C10: Introduction to General Astronomy Astro 7A: Introduction to Astrophysics Astro 250: Introduction to High Performance Computing Physics 7A: Introductory Mechanics ADJUNCT INSTRUCTOR (New York University) Observational Astronomy Spring 2013 UC BERKELEY TEACHING CONFERENCE Developer and instructor of a mandatory workshop for first time graduate student instructors COURSEWORK IN TEACHING DEVELOPMENT (UC Berkeley) Physics 198: Progressive Physics Education Physics 198: Physics Pedagogy Seminar Spring 2014 | Astro 9: Introduction to Scientific Computing Sole Instructor: in charge of syllabus design and instruction | Summer 2020 |
| GRADUATE STUDENT INSTRUCTOR (UC Berkeley) Astro C10: Introduction to General Astronomy Astro 7A: Introduction to Astrophysics Fall 2017 Astro 250: Introduction to High Performance Computing Physics 7A: Introductory Mechanics Fall 2013 ADJUNCT INSTRUCTOR (New York University) Observational Astronomy Spring 2013 UC BERKELEY TEACHING CONFERENCE Developer and instructor of a mandatory workshop for first time graduate student instructors COURSEWORK IN TEACHING DEVELOPMENT (UC Berkeley) Physics 198: Progressive Physics Education Physics 198: Physics Pedagogy Seminar Spring 2014 | HEAD GRADUATE STUDENT INSTRUCTOR (UC Berkeley) | |
| Astro C10: Introduction to General Astronomy Astro 7A: Introduction to Astrophysics Astro 250: Introduction to High Performance Computing Physics 7A: Introductory Mechanics ADJUNCT INSTRUCTOR (New York University) Observational Astronomy Spring 2013 UC Berkeley Teaching Conference Developer and instructor of a mandatory workshop for first time graduate student instructors COURSEWORK IN TEACHING DEVELOPMENT (UC Berkeley) Physics 198: Progressive Physics Education Physics 198: Physics Pedagogy Seminar Fall 2019 Fall 2017 Fall 2017 Spring 2013 | Physics 7A: Introductory Mechanics | Spring 2014 |
| Astro 7A: Introduction to Astrophysics Astro 250: Introduction to High Performance Computing Physics 7A: Introductory Mechanics ADJUNCT INSTRUCTOR (New York University) Observational Astronomy Spring 2013 UC BERKELEY TEACHING CONFERENCE Developer and instructor of a mandatory workshop for first time graduate student instructors COURSEWORK IN TEACHING DEVELOPMENT (UC Berkeley) Physics 198: Progressive Physics Education Physics 198: Physics Pedagogy Seminar Fall 2014 Spring 2015 Physics 198: Physics Pedagogy Seminar | Graduate Student Instructor (UC Berkeley) | |
| Astro 250: Introduction to High Performance Computing Physics 7A: Introductory Mechanics ADJUNCT INSTRUCTOR (New York University) Observational Astronomy Spring 2013 UC Berkeley Teaching Conference Developer and instructor of a mandatory workshop for first time graduate student instructors COURSEWORK IN TEACHING DEVELOPMENT (UC Berkeley) Physics 198: Progressive Physics Education Physics 198: Physics Pedagogy Seminar Spring 2014 | Astro C10: Introduction to General Astronomy | Fall 2019 |
| Physics 7A: Introductory Mechanics ADJUNCT INSTRUCTOR (New York University) Observational Astronomy UC BERKELEY TEACHING CONFERENCE Developer and instructor of a mandatory workshop for first time graduate student instructors COURSEWORK IN TEACHING DEVELOPMENT (UC Berkeley) Physics 198: Progressive Physics Education Physics 198: Pedagogy Seminar Spring 2014 | Astro 7A: Introduction to Astrophysics | Fall 2017 |
| ADJUNCT INSTRUCTOR (New York University) Observational Astronomy UC Berkeley Teaching Conference Developer and instructor of a mandatory workshop for first time graduate student instructors Coursework in Teaching Development (UC Berkeley) Physics 198: Progressive Physics Education Spring 2015 Physics 198: Physics Pedagogy Seminar Spring 2014 | Astro 250: Introduction to High Performance Computing | Spring 2017 |
| Observational Astronomy UC BERKELEY TEACHING CONFERENCE Developer and instructor of a mandatory workshop for first time graduate student instructors COURSEWORK IN TEACHING DEVELOPMENT (UC Berkeley) Physics 198: Progressive Physics Education Spring 2015 Physics 198: Physics Pedagogy Seminar Spring 2014 | Physics 7A: Introductory Mechanics | Fall 2013 |
| UC BERKELEY TEACHING CONFERENCE Developer and instructor of a mandatory workshop for first time graduate student instructors COURSEWORK IN TEACHING DEVELOPMENT (UC Berkeley) Physics 198: Progressive Physics Education Spring 2015 Physics 198: Physics Pedagogy Seminar Spring 2014 | Adjunct Instructor (New York University) | |
| Developer and instructor of a mandatory workshop for first time graduate student instructors Coursework in Teaching Development (UC Berkeley) Physics 198: Progressive Physics Education Spring 2015 Physics 198: Physics Pedagogy Seminar Spring 2014 | Observational Astronomy | Spring 2013 |
| for first time graduate student instructors Coursework in Teaching Development (UC Berkeley) Physics 198: Progressive Physics Education Physics 198: Physics Pedagogy Seminar Spring 2014 | UC BERKELEY TEACHING CONFERENCE | |
| COURSEWORK IN TEACHING DEVELOPMENT (UC Berkeley) Physics 198: Progressive Physics Education Physics 198: Physics Pedagogy Seminar Spring 2014 | Developer and instructor of a mandatory workshop | Fall 2014 |
| Physics 198: Progressive Physics Education Spring 2015 Physics 198: Physics Pedagogy Seminar Spring 2014 | for first time graduate student instructors | |
| Physics 198: Physics Pedagogy Seminar Spring 2014 | Coursework in Teaching Development (UC Berkeley) | |
| | Physics 198: Progressive Physics Education | Spring 2015 |
| Physics 375: Professional Preparation in Teaching Physics Fall 2013 | Physics 198: Physics Pedagogy Seminar | Spring 2014 |
| | Physics 375: Professional Preparation in Teaching Physics | Fall 2013 |

Abiqail E. Polin 4

LEADERSHIP, OUTREACH & SERVICE

Public Talks

| Carnegie Astronomy Lecture Series, Huntington Library, Pasadena CA | May 2023 |
|--|----------|
| AAS Journal Author Series | Jan 2023 |
| Astronomy on Tap, Pasadena CA | Oct 2022 |
| Wonderfest Science Series, Virtual Talk | Jan 2021 |
| Radio Interview: Women in STEM w/ KPOO-FM | Mar 2020 |
| Wonderfest Science Envoy Speaks at the Verdi Club, San Francisco, CA | Feb 2020 |
| Berkeley Art Museum and Pacific Film Archive, Berkeley, CA | Nov 2018 |

Leadership & Service Positions

| Carnegie Postdoc Representative | 2021-2023 |
|---------------------------------|-----------|
| | |

Caltech TAPIR Seminar Organizer 2021-2023

CASSI Science Mentor

2021-2022

CASSI is a 10 week internship and educational program at Carnegie designed to improve undergraduate students' fluency with research and communication.

Wonderfest Science Envoy

2019-2020

A program funded by the Gordon and Betty Moore Foundation that identifies PhD students who show particular science-popularization promise. The program helps us to develop the subtle art and science of public outreach. The program's participants emerge as articulate Science Envoys.

UC Berkeley Society for Women in the Physical Sciences:

| v v | v | |
|-----------------------|---|-------------------------|
| Astronomy Coordinator | | Fall 2015 - Spring 2019 |
| Mentoring Coordinator | | Fall 2014 - Spring 2016 |

Berkeley Connect Fellow

Fall 2014 - Spring 2017

Berkeley Connect is a teaching and mentorship program intended to strengthen the relationship between undergraduate students and the Physics Department. As a Fellow, I contributed to curriculum design, led class meetings, and mentored students one-on-one.

Respect is Part of Research: Founding Member and Peer Facilitator 2014 - 2016 RPR is a graduate student group that runs annual peer-led sexual assault and sexual harassment prevention workshops for incoming first-year graduate students. RPR's primary mission is to create a respectful, positive working environment where everyone can do their best science.

Compass Program Organizer/Instructor/Research Mentor Summer 2014 The Berkeley Compass Project is a Physics graduate student-run organization that aims to improve the experiences of undergraduate students from under-represented groups interested in STEM.

Anonymous Peer Reviewer for: ApJ, ApJL & MNRAS

Abiqail E. Polin 5

Publications [ADS Link]

Summary: 18 journal articles, 3 as first author, 7 identifying supernovae belonging to a newly discovered class of transients, which matched our modeled theoretical predictions

 Using Anisotropies as a Forensic Tool for Decoding Supernova Remnants Polin, A., P. Duffell, and D. Milisavljevic The Astrophysical Journal Letters 940, L28, (2022).

2. Nebular Models of Sub-Chandrasekhar Mass Type Ia Supernovae: Clues to the Origin of Ca-rich Transients

Polin, A., P. E. Nugent, and D. Kasen The Astrophysical Journal, 906, 65 (2021).

3. Observational Predictions for Sub-Chandrasekhar Mass Explosions: Further Evidence for Multiple Progenitor Systems for Type Ia Supernovae

Polin, A., P. E. Nugent, and D. Kasen The Astrophysical Journal, 873, 84 (2019).

4. SN 2020jgb: A Peculiar Type Ia Supernova Triggered by a Massive Helium-Shell Detonation in a Star-Forming Galaxy

Liu, C., A. Miller, **A. Polin**, and 25 colleagues. arXiv:2209.04463. accepted/in press The Astrophysical Journal (2023).

5. SN 2021zny: an early flux excess combined with late-time oxygen emission suggests a double white dwarf merger event

Dimitriadis, G., and 30 colleagues including **A. Polin**. *accepted/in press* MNRAS (2023).

6. SN 2016dsg: A Thermonuclear Explosion Involving a Thick Helium Shell Dong, Y., S. Valenti, A. Polin, and 29 colleagues. The Astrophysical Journal, 934, 2, (2022).

7. The origin and evolution of the normal Type Ia SN 2018aoz with infant-phase reddening and excess emission

Qi Ni, Y., D. Moon, M. Drout, **A. Polin**, and 40 colleagues arXiv:2206.12437, *submitted to* The Astrophysical Journal (2022).

8. The Absolute Magnitudes of 1991T-like Supernovae Phillips, M., and 22 colleagues including **A. Polin**. The Astrophysical Journal, 938, 47, (2022).

9. Physical Properties of the Host Galaxies of Ca-rich Transients Dong, Y., D. Milisavljevic, and 9 colleagues, including A. Polin The Astrophysical Journal, 927, 2, (2022).

- Infant-phase Reddening by Surface Fe-peak Elements in a Normal Type Ia Supernova Qi Ni, Y., D. Moon, M. Drout, A. Polin, and 40 colleagues Nature Astronomy, cover article February, (2022).
- 11. The Zwicky Transient Facility Census of the Local Universe I: Systematic search for Calcium rich qap transients reveal three related spectroscopic sub-classes

Abigail E. Polin

De, Kishalay, and 49 colleagues including **A. Polin** The Astrophysical Journal, 905, 58 (2020).

12. ZTF Early Observations of Type Ia Supernovae. III. Early-time Colors As a Test for Explosion Models and Multiple Populations

Bulla, M. and 24 colleagues including **A. Polin** The Astrophysical Journal, 902, 1, 48 (2020).

 Strong Calcium Emission Indicates that the Ultraviolet-flashing SN Ia 2019yvq Was the Result of a Sub-Chandrasekhar Mass Double-detonation Explosion
 Siebert, M. R.; G. Dimitriadis, A. Polin, and R. J. Foley
 The Astrophysical Journal Letters, 900, 2, L27, (2020).

 The Spectacular Ultraviolet Flash from the Peculiar Type Ia Supernova 2019yvq Miller, A. A., M. R. Magee, A. Polin, and 42 colleagues The Astrophysical Journal, 898, 1, 56 (2020).

15. Ca hnk: The Calcium-rich Transient Supernova 2016hnk from a Helium Shell Detonation of a Sub-Chandrasekhar White Dwarf

Jacobson-Galán, W., A. Polin, R. J. Foley, and 11 colleagues The Astrophysical Journal, 896, 2, 165 (2020).

16. ZTF 18aaqeasu (SN 2018byg): A Massive Helium-shell Double Detonation on a Sub-Chandrasekhar Mass White Dwarf

De, K., M. Kasliwal, A. Polin, and 27 colleagues The Astrophysical Journal Letters, 873, L18 (2019).

17. K2 Observations of SN 2018oh Reveal a Two-Component Rising Light Curve for a Type Ia Supernova

Dimitriadis G., R. J. Foley, A. Rest, D. Kasen, A. L. Piro, A. Polin, and 144 colleagues The Astrophysical Journal Letters, 870L, 1D (2019).

18. Gravitational Wave Hotspots: Ranking Potential Locations of Single-Source Gravitational Wave Emission

Simon J., A. Polin, A. Lommen, B. Stappers, L.S. Finn, F. Jenet and B. Christy The Astrophysical Journal, 784, 60 (2014).